Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
You are educated, I appreciate that.
I wonder if you are a slender beauty.
Raise your head.
Your family name Zhen is disrespectful to the Emperor.
[His name is Yin Zhen]
Your Majesty, the name was bestowed upon
my family as an honor by the prior emperor.
I see.
Mother, it reminds me
how the Zhens were known for their beautiful girls in history.
This one is no exception.
Come forward.
Very well-mannered.
[The Empress Dowager attempted to fail her.]
"The slender beauties in King Chu's palace
over the spring time fade like flowers."
But my palace nourishes beautiful souls.
I hope you will enjoy living here.
Who is the other girl next to her?
Sun Miaoqing, 16, sister of the Chief of Suzhou Clothing Services
Sun Miaoqing behaved offensively to Her Majesty.
She shall never attend the Selection.
Bestow the sachet upon Zhen Huan.
(Your Majesty, please forgive me!)
It did not turn out as hoped.
Don't be upset. Living in the palace is the envy of many.
Besides, we will be able to take care of each other in the palace.
The messenger eunuch must be on his way
to inform your parents. They will be elated.
But Meizhuang, I had no intention of living here.
No, but Heaven did.
Your life is destined not to be ordinary.
But His Majesty...
Miss Sun was simply startled.
She meant no offence.
We have to be meticulously careful from now on.
Greetings, My Ladies.
I was instructed to conduct you to the gate, My Ladies.
I'm pleased to extend my congratulations.
Here they are.
I hope everything went well.
Take care, Meizhuang.
You as well.
[the name list of new concubines]
“The slender beauties in King Chu's palace.”
Her Majesty the Empress requests to see you.
- Show her in.
- Yes.
I would like to congratulate Your Majesty on the new concubines.
Thank you.
We are all happy that Your Majesty was very pleased today.
Well, I had to make do with what was selected.
You can't be serious.
I heard that Miss Shen bears some
resemblance of Concubine Estime.
And Miss Zhen looks exactly like ...
Just a little bit.
That is quite enough.
I'm curious to know what rank Your Majesty
would like to grant Miss Zhen.
How about Noble Lady?
Nobel Lady...
sounds good.
In this case, there would be four Noble Ladies:
Lady Fuca from the Manchu Banners,
Lady Borjigin from the Mongolian Banners,
and two from the Han Banners.
Two? Who is the other one?
Shen Meizhuang.
Her father's position is higher than Zhen's.
I understand that Your Majesty holds
the Han banners in high regard.
But this may seem unfair to the other two Banners.
On that note, she will be an Attendant.
[the 7th rank, while Noble Lady being the 6th]
It's not appropriate for Han banners to begin with a high rank.
Yes, Your Majesty.
However, I wish to give her an honorary name.
I will inform the Household Department to propose a name.
No, I have one in mind.
Come here.
Sourire.
[meaning "smile"]
It is a special name.
[The Empress quotes a poem using the character]
I like her smiling face.
So pretty!
Vermilion, are we almost home?
Yes, look at the cheering crowd.
Here she comes!
Congratulations!
Father.
Zhen Yuandao and family greets My Lady.
Peace to You, My Lady.
What is going on?
Stand up quickly!
My Lady, this is how we should greet you.
My Lady, you are a member of the imperial family now.
Vermilion and Jade, help my parents up quickly.
Thank You, My Lady.
It's cold out here. Let's go inside.
After you, My Lady.
Mind your step.
I will be away from home shortly.
My Lady, please stand!
And I made my parents kneel to me.
(Parents politely asking her to stand)
Please let me finish.
Although I am a member of the imperial family,
I will only be your daughter before I move out.
I will not stand if I cannot fulfill my filial piety.
I am proud of you, daughter.
Please stand up.
Good morning, Your Highness.
Her Highness is awake.
[Fuzi]
Your Highness, it was brought to my notice that
His Majesty stayed with Attendant Joie last night.
His Majesty had not visited the harem for ten days.
Why did he visit that bitch?
It's been more than a month since her miscarriage.
What does she want?
Watch your stupid fingers!
I beg your pardon, Your Highness.
What were you doing?
You did it on purpose!
My room is not a circus!
Take her out!
Please spare me, Your Highness!
Come with me!
Please spare me! Your Highness!
Your Highness!
Please forgive me!
Your Majesty, it seems that Consort Fleur
is not going to appear today.
Shall we dismiss?
A consort must greet the Empress every morning.
We will wait for her.
Distribute tea.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Spring, serve the tea.
She's never on time.
Her Brother is General Nian.
(Attendant Joie)
She's the apple of His Majesty's eye.
(Consort Astuce)
But this is the Empress in His Majesty's eyes.
(Noble Lady Cao)
I haven't seen Consort Honnête for some time.
She's bed-ridden.
(left: Concubine Estime)
(right: Concubine Beauté)
Her Highness Consort Fleur.
Peace to Your Highness.
You may rise.
Attendant Joie is early.
How are you feeling today?
I thank Your Highness for asking.
I did not feel very well earlier, but I could afford
no delay in paying my respects to Her Majesty.
That was really thoughtful of you.
I hope you will soon recuperate for another pregnancy.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, Attendant Joie
has been feeling much better than before.
I noticed the healthy glow on her face.
Consort Astuce looks quite voluptuous.
His Majesty will be happy to see you.
Thank you.
Oh, I forgot His Majesty never visits you.
Sorry for mentioning that.
It's fine.
All right. A family should not be standing for a talk.
Please sit down.
I thank Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Please sit and have some tea.
Spring, tea for Her Highness.
Is this Longjing tea from last year?
Old tea smells of mildew however well preserved.
I gave away mine to my maids.
I received this year's pre-rain Longjing.
I will let Song Zhi bring some to Your Majesty.
Thank you, but His Majesty offered that to me as well.
I gave it to Consort Astuce and the Third Prince.
Of course, it must be a rarity for them.
Feel free to ask me for help
if the Third Prince needs anything else.
The Third Prince would never bother anyone with trivial matters,
as a result of a good upbringing.
Indeed. And the Third Prince will please
His Majesty with his studiousness.
When His Majesty is pleased,
he will give the Third Prince tea and gold leaves.
The Third Prince is the eldest son of His Majesty.
He will be an example to the Fourth Prince and the Fifth Prince.
(sigh) The palace is not fully furnished
due to our rushed move-in.
Especially the Palace of Benevolence.
I intend to have your it better decorated on a nice day.
It will be a more pleasant for Your Majesty to live here.
Thank you. But I would prefer a frugal lifestyle.
The imperial family is on a budget.
I admire your constant willingness to feel content.
I always feel ill at ease living in my lavish palace.
That is because your palace was occupied by
Consort Bonheur of the prior emperor.
She was greatly honored for being a prolific mother.
I am leaving now.
Your Majesty, me as well.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Your Majesty can always quickly quiet down her shrill arrogance.
But she wasn't wrong.
Our palace sustains an atmosphere of goodwill.
(Autumn)
His Majesty selected it for Your Majesty
in honor of your benevolence.
She was just jealous of Your Highness's palace.
Consort Bonheur's son rebelled against the prior emperor.
How dare she curse my palace!
Your Highness must not take that sick woman seriously.
Whoever disrespects Your Highness is offending His Majesty.
(sneer) You know the rules.
I simply know the truth that His Majesty
favors Your Highness the most.
Indeed. Palace of Earthly Honor shows
Your Highness's status in the palace.
Earth represents the Empress while Heaven the Emperor.
Evidently, His Majesty sees Your Highness as his Empress.
His Majesty respects the Empress as a matter of formality.
Your Highness takes priority.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
We have arrived.
Is this the sister of Miss Zhen.
No, we both are her personal maids.
Even a maid is dressed so nicely.
The Zhen family must be very distinguished.
My Lady is waiting for you.
Please follow me.
Greetings ...
Make yourself at home.
I have no friend or family in Beijing.
Thank you for letting me stay here.
I am your friend and family in Beijing.
Please have a seat, Lady An.
This is ...
This is my aunt. She came along to take care of me.
Madam, please sit down.
Thank you.
I can never thank you enough for your help.
My pleasure. Don't mention it.
How was the trip?
The inn keeper was trying to rip her off.
But I called his bluff. (chuckle)
Thank you so much for helping me out!
Vermilion is really smart!
May I ask when you were born?
I'm seventeen, born on the 17th of April.
I am sixteen, born on the 9th of February.
You will be my little sister!
Certainly, dear sister.
Huan'er.
Father, you are still up.
Have a seat.
Thanks.
You have been taking good care of Lady An.
You are now a dependable grown-up.
There's something I have to tell you.
If you cannot ensure a place in His Majesty's affections,
you will have to stay out of the rivalries.
You have no obligation to be
the favorite concubine of His Majesty.
I simply wish you a peaceful life in the harem.
I will always keep that in mind.
I shall bring no distress to my family.
Very well.
You are allowed to have dowry maids to live with you in the palace.
They must be competent and trustworthy.
Do you have anyone in mind?
Yes. I will have Vermilion and Jade as my dowry maids.
You girls grew up together. They are the ideal choice.
Especially Jade, she's ...
In fact, she is your sister.
My sister?
Please don't tell your mother.
I had ...
I met a Han woman a long time ago...
And we had Jade.
No wonder you never allowed Jade to do menial jobs.
I could not marry her mother because
her family offended His Majesty.
To protect Jade and yourself,
His Majesty must not know her background.
It was all my fault.
You did what you had to.
I will be on the lookout for
a good family to arrange for Jade's marriage.
She will be most grateful for your help.
I have always treated her as my sister and always will.
Thank you.
My Lady is moving into the palace soon.
Yes.
I heard she is allowed to have dowry maids.
And?
Are you going?
Where to?
The palace.
I will be wherever My Lady is.
We will always be best friends.
Are you not going?
I'm not sure.
My Lady is like sister to you!
It's not about that.
I was just worried about the rest of the family.
I would miss them so much.
Hey, don't worry!
They will be taken good care of.
By the Grace of Heaven, His Majesty awards
Zhen Huan the seventh-ranking title of Attendant.
She is bestowed the honorary name Sourire.
Attendant Sourire will move into the palace
on September 15th. This is His Majesty's edict.
I thank His Majesty.
By the Grace of Heaven, His Majesty awards
An Lingrong the eighth-ranking title of Companion.
Companion An will move in on September 15th.
This is His Majesty's edict.
I thank His Majesty.
You may rise.
Mr. Zhen, this is Madam Orchid.
She will be teaching the imperial etiquette.
Peace to you, Madam.
Attendant Sourire is very well mannered.
Than you, sir.
Attendant Xia was not as friendly.
She taught the madam a lesson.
I bow in respect before Attendant Sourire and
Companion An. Peace to you, My Ladies.
You are a respected madam in the palace.
Please do not bow to us as our teacher.
Yes, My Lady.
Sir, thank you for coming on such a hot day.
(chuckle) Thank you for your generosity.
Madam Orchid was an etiquette trainer
for the concubines of the prior emperor.
You both will benefit a lot from her teaching.
Thank you, sir.
Since Attendant Sourire and Companion An are living together,
I hope you don't mind teaching them both at the same time.
My pleasure.
Would you like some tea in the drawing room, sir?
Thank you, but I have to visit other families.
Please go ahead, sir.
Goodbye.
My Ladies, there were eight girls selected this year.
The Han Banners will move in after
the Manchu and the Mongolian Banners.
You two and Nobel Lady Shen will move in on the same day.
Noble Lady Shen?
(gasp) Meizhuang is a Noble Lady!
Ah, congratulations to her!
I'm excited that we can move in later
and take care of one another.
What an arrogant girl!
Miss Xia likes to show off her father's high rank.
Now that she has the title of Attendant,
she even lectures the etiquette instructor.
She's quite a bully.
I look forward to seeing her.
But I heard that a girl shut her down at the Selection?
It was Zhen Huan.
His Majesty quite likes her.
She's an Attendant, too.
Sounds like we are about to have a party.
Tell the instructor at the Xias'
not to make the effort to teach.
I believe the instructor knows what to do.
Every province is in deficit.
Taxes are always deferred.
Every province is indebted by millions.
The people are suffering in poverty.
But where did all the money go?
May peace be restored in Your Majesty.
Money will take care of itself in my humble opinion.
Things will work out.
Your Majesty, please select one.
Did I allow you in?
But Your Majesty, it's time that I come in.
Attendant Joie.
I'm sorry, Your Majesty.
Attendant Joie's name tag has been withdrawn.
I'm afraid it will not be presented for two months.
Why?
Consort Fleur commanded that Attendant Joie
take a break to recover from her miscarriage.
That's typical of Consort Fleur.
Never mind, she's probably right.
I will visit her instead.
Yes.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Where is she?
I'm sorry, Your Majesty. Her Highness was
feeling unwell and went to sleep.
That is early.
I shall leave if that's the case.
I should visit Consort Astuce and the Third Prince.
Don't ever come back if you leave.
Somebody's naughty tonight.
Somebody's naughty having not visited me for 2 weeks.
He has probably forgotten me.
Nonsense.
How could I ever forget my cheeky monkey?
You smell so good.
It's Pleasancy, the incense Your Majesty exclusively gave me.
That is the scent that I like.
No one else deserves it.
Every household has its master and mistress.
We address them as "Your Majesty" in the palace:
the Emperor, the Empress, and the Empress Dowager
The other concubines are referred to as "My Lady".
We say the Emperor has one "primary" wife
and many "secondary" wives. [the Dishu System]
Consort Fleur is the favorite wife of His Majesty.
You may call her "Your Highness" to show respect.
"Your Highness"? [pinyin: niang niang]
Yes, but it's not for everyone.
The person must be the head of a palace,
and ranked Concubine (fifth) or above.
The head of a palace lives in the main chamber of
the palace and takes charge of her palace.
Concubines of the top five ranks are limited in number,
but the lower ranks are flexible.
Is Companion the lowest rank?
No, the lowest is Escort, the ninth rank.
So the concubines are in nine ranks,
just like the officials.
Why is it called "Escort"?
Escorts are not much different than maids
but they can accompany His Majesty overnight.
They will be promoted to Companion if His Majesty likes.
Every concubine can only be promoted to the nearest upper rank.
Peace to Your Highness.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Her Majesty the Empress has
assigned residences to the new concubines.
She would appreciate Your Highness's opinion.
Go ahead.
Noble Lady Fuca, Manchu, was assigned
the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Noble Lady Borjigin, Mogolian,
the Palace of Accumulated Purity.
Noble Lady Shen, Han,
the Palace of Universal Happiness.
Attendant Sourire, Han,
the Palace of Celestial Favor.
Hold on ...
Attendant Sourire?
Attendant Sourire is the daughter of
the Deputy Minister of Judicial Review.
She is the only new concubine with
an honorary name despite her rank.
Is she the talkative girl at the Selection?
Yes, Your Highness.
Was it His Majesty's decision to assign her
the Palace of Celestial Favor?
It was the decision of the Empress.
His Majesty knows nothing about it.
The Palace of Celestial Favor is spacious
and close to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
That is a rather flattering palace.
The Empress spares no effort to please His Majesty.
She would very much like a sidekick in place
to have more control over His Majesty.
No, that girl does not deserve
His Majesty's "celestial favor".
Now, I wish to tell you about His Majesty the Emperor.
His Majesty was titled State Prince
and married the sororal niece of the current Empress Dowager.
She was a well respected lady from the Ula-Nara family,
and deeply loved by His Majesty.
Unfortunately, she passed after three years
when giving birth to the Second Prince.
And the Second Prince was not saved at birth.
His Majesty is profoundly sad about her death.
He honored her as Empress Première.
Such is the Emperor of an undying love.
What about the current Empress?
I heard that she is the daughter of a secondary wife.
You should not judge Her Majesty by that.
Her Majesty is a kind, motherly presence in the palace.
I'm sorry.
Her Majesty is the younger sister of Empress Première.
She became the step empress after her sister's death.
His Majesty has great respect for her.
Is there any other palace available?
Yes, the Palace of Pearl Jade is vacant.
But it used to be occupied by Noble Lady Parfum.
And it's small and distant.
And it used to be a small theater.
It became the residence for concubines who fell from grace.
The chamber is considered bad luck.
Bad luck?
Lady Parfum had a miscarriage and
got banished to the Cold Palace.
It has nothing to do with luck.
If the new girl is lucky enough to get pregnant like her,
the Empress will be even more pleased.
Yes, Your Highness.
Was the chamber assigned to anyone?
No.
Prepare it for Attendant Sourire.
What about Miss Xia,
the girl with an interesting name?
The Empress advised His Majesty to grant her the title of Attendant.
Seems like the Empress is trying to buy her off.
I'm not sure.
Keep an eye on her in case she's an ally of the Empress.
She's assigned to live with Lady Fuca.
They will get along (sneer).
I heard that His Majesty's favorite wife is Consort Fleur.
Yes, Her Highness is the younger sister of General Nian.
His Majesty has been exclusively devoted
to her since they got married.
But why isn't Her Highness ranked above Consort?
Good question. Because Her Highness has no children.
Her Highness is already a Consort without having a child.
As a result of His Majesty's devotion.
But that is not a paramount consideration.
Your priority would always be having a child.
Either a son or a daughter.
They are the only person you can rely upon in the palace.
(chuckle) Of course, Consort Fleur is in
high favor and still young to have children.
I heard that Consort Fleur is exceptionally beautiful.
She's the best of the Han Banners,
or even of all the eight Banners.
That is why she's the favorite of His Majesty?
Poet Li Bai wrote
"Love for a pretty face fades at the aging pace."
[booklet of residence assignment]
Your Majesty, Consort Fleur assigned
Attendant Sourire to Palace of Pearl Jade.
I feel sorry for her.
The chamber is isolated and poorly furnished.
It used to be a theater before Lady Parfum stayed in.
How could she do something without consulting Your Majesty?
Don't sound like you knew her from yesterday.
But His Majesty likes that about her.
Here's another gray strand of hair.
Who did His Majesty select for tonight?
No one. His Majesty had a busy day.
He might be awake.
It's okay.
His Majesty is fond of Attendant Sourire.
I wish to have devilwood planted in her yard to ward off bad luck.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Living in the palace is like swimming in deep water.
You must take the best care of yourself
and be most tolerant of other concubines.
Especially Consort Fleur.
We all would be happy if you have the
blessing to become a prominent consort.
But that is not as important as your life.
I will always behave with propriety.
Please don't worry.
Yurao, please take take of mom and dad for me.
I will.
My Lady, it's time to leave.
I have to go now.
I will miss you all so much.
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.